<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on GRASP-suite</title>
    <link>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on GRASP-suite</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>asr.GRASP</title>
      <link>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/graspcmd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/graspcmd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;grasp-command-line-interface-cli&#34;&gt;GRASP command-line interface (CLI)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a command-line interface of GRASP that can prove useful if you want to automate tasks, run reconstructions on your own dedicated hardware, and/or access the latest features.    This version is essentially a command-line interface to the backend features of the web-based service. It is worth noting that the web-version has the advantage of a visual user interface, but that also means that it may lack the latest functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command-line version allows access to a variety of indel inference approaches. Beyond the default bi-directional edge encoding (BE), indels are available by either Position Specific (PS), or Simple Indel Coding (SIC). Regardless of encoding, indels can be inferred using either Parsimony (P) or Maximum Likelihood (ML) methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives six methods - PS-P, PS-ML, SIC-P, SIC-ML, BE-P, BE-ML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command-line interface is implemented in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bodenlab/bnkit&#34;&gt;bnkit&lt;/a&gt; as a class &lt;code&gt;asr.GRASP&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;asrgrasp-what-can-it-do&#34;&gt;asr.GRASP: What can it do?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;asr.GRASP accepts an alignment (FASTA or Clustal formats) and a phylogenetic tree (Newick format) with concordant labels, to infer ancestor sequences by joint or marginal reconstruction by maximum likelihood. In the process, the program also infers insertion and deletion events, which are internally represented via partial-order graphs; it also identifies the &lt;em&gt;most supported&lt;/em&gt; path of sequence inclusions at each ancestor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program can save all ancestor sequences (in the case of joint reconstruction) or one sequence (in the case of marginal reconstrution; optionally with character state distributions as a TSV file). It can save the partial-order graphs in JSON or as DOT files, which can be visualised with GraphViz. It can also re-save the tree with assigned ancestor labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GRASP was designed primarily for protein sequences but the command-line version incorporates DNA models too. At this stage we have not tested DNA sequence functionality extensively, nor have we developed specific features around DNA sequences (codon-centric analyses, user-provided background stats, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;access-through-docker&#34;&gt;Access through Docker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GRASP is available through Docker Hub at &lt;code&gt;gabefoley/grasp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have docker installed you can&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;docker run -it -v {full path to where your data is located}:/data gabefoley/grasp grasp -aln /data/{name of your alignment file}.aln -nwk /data/{name of your newick file}.nwk -out /data
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;for example, for me the command looks like (I have test_6.aln and test_6.nwk sitting in a /data folder):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;docker run -it -v /Users/coolusername/Documents/code/grasp/data:/data grasp-docker grasp -aln /data/test_6.aln -nwk /data/test_6.nwk -out /data
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This should give you a file, GRASP_ancestors.fasta appearing in folder: /Users/coolusername/Documents/code/grasp/data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;asrgrasp-how-do-i-make-it-work-on-my-computer&#34;&gt;asr.GRASP: How do I make it work on my computer?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you will need Java version 8 or newer. Any operating system with Java should work, including Mac OS, MS Windows and Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you have a choice: you can clone/download &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bodenlab/bnkit&#34;&gt;bnkit&lt;/a&gt; in its entirety. You may need JUnit 5 testing to get everything working; this is only required if you want to run software tests, say if you are a developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, just download the pre-compiled version with all indel inference methods &lt;a href=&#34;archive/bnkit.jar&#34;&gt;bnkit JAR file&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, the legacy version &lt;a href=&#34;archive/bnkit_legacy.jar&#34;&gt;bnkit JAR file&lt;/a&gt;, which we keep to ensure reproducibility of results presented in the original papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;asrgrasp-how-do-i-run-it&#34;&gt;asr.GRASP: How do I run it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the jar file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a bash script grasp that contains the following two lines, replacing the path with the path to your downloaded jar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;java -jar -Xmx16g &amp;lt;/path/to/filename.jar&amp;gt; $@&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(the &lt;code&gt;-Xmx&lt;/code&gt; is optional; see below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change permissions on the bash script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;chmod 755 grasp
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place grasp where you store your executable files, for example - /usr/local/bin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;mv grasp /usr/local/bin`
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check it works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-console&#34; data-lang=&#34;console&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;grasp -h
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This will print out the arguments that specifies your input data and options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical command may look like this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;grasp -aln 500_2112_dhad_18032019.aln -nwk r_500_2112_dhad_18032019.nwk -out recon_0500.aln -verbose -gap -thr 5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Full help information -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Usage: asr.GRASP
  [-a | --aln &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;]
  [-n | --nwk &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;]
  {-o | --output-folder &amp;lt;foldername&amp;gt;} (default is current working folder)
  {-pre | --prefix &amp;lt;stub&amp;gt;}
  {-rf | --rates-file &amp;lt;filename&amp;gt;}
  {-s | --substitution-model &amp;lt;JTT(default)|Dayhoff|LG|WAG|JC|Yang&amp;gt;}
  {-t | --threads &amp;lt;number&amp;gt;}
  {-j | --joint (default)}
  {-m | --marginal &amp;lt;branchpoint-id&amp;gt;}
  {--indel-method &amp;lt;methodname&amp;gt;} (select one from BEP(default) BEML SICP SICML PSP PSML)
  {--nogap}
  {--nonibble}
  {--save-as &amp;lt;list-of-formats&amp;gt;} (select multiple from FASTA CLUSTAL TREE DISTRIB POGS DOT TREES)
  {--time}{--verbose}{--help}
Inference is a two-stage process:
  (1) A history of indel events is inferred by either maximum likelihood or maximum parsimony and
  mapped onto the tree to determine what positions contain actual sequence content
  (2) For each ancestral position, the most probable character is assigned to each phylogenetic branch
  point when performing a joint reconstruction. Alternatively, for each
  position at a nominated branch point, the probability distribution over all possible
  characters is inferred when performing a marginal reconstruction.
  Finally, edges are drawn to represent all inferred combinations of indels to form an ancestor POG
  with nodes that can form a valid sequence with inferred content; a preferred path
  through the POG is then inferred, nominating a single, best supported sequence.
Mode of character inference:
  -j (or --joint) activates joint reconstruction (default),
  -m (or --marginal) activates marginal reconstruction (requires a branch-point to be nominated)

Required arguments:
  -a (or --aln) must specify the name of a multiple-sequence alignment file on FASTA or CLUSTAL format
  -a (or --nwk) must specify the name of a phylogenetic-tree file on Newick format

Optional arguments:
  -o (or --output-folder) specifies the folder that will be used to save output files,
    e.g. inferred ancestor or ancestors, tree, etc. as specified by format
  -sa (or --save-as) lists the files and formats to be generated (see below)
  --save-all nominates all
  -pre (or --prefix) specifies a stub that is added to result filenames (default is the prefix of the alignment file)
  -i (or --indel-method) specifies what method to use for inferring indels (see below)
  -s (or --substitution-model) specifies what evolutionary model to use for inferring character states (see below)
  -rf (or --rates-file) specifies a tabulated file with relative, position-specific rates
    e.g. as produced by IQ-TREE
  --nogap means that the gap-character is excluded in the resulting output (when the format allows)
  --nonibble de-activates the removal of indices in partial order graphs that cannot form a path from start to end
  --verbose prints out information about steps undertaken, and --time the time it took to finish
  -h (or --help) will print out this screen

Files/formats:
  FASTA: sequences (most preferred path at each ancestor, gapped or not gapped)
  CLUSTAL: sequences (most preferred path at each ancestor, gapped)
  TREE: phylogenetic tree with ancestor nodes labelled
  DISTRIB: character distributions for each position (indexed by POG, only available for marginal reconstruction)
  POGS: partial-order graphs of ancestors
  DOT: partial-order graphs of ancestors in DOT format
  TREES: position-specific trees with ancestor states labelled

Indel-methods:
  BEP: bi-directional edge (maximum) parsimony
  BEML: bi-directional edge maximum likelihood (uses uniform evolutionary model akin to JC)
  SICP: simple indel-coding (maximum) parsimony (based on Simmons and Ochoterena)
  SICML: simple indel-coding maximum likelihood (uses uniform evolutionary model)
  PSP: position-specific (maximum) parsimony
  PSML: position-specific maximum likelihood (uses uniform evolutionary model)
  Add &amp;#39;*&amp;#39; to method name for less conservative setting (if available)

Substitution-models:
  JTT: Jones-Taylor-Thornton (protein; default)
  Dayhoff: Dayhoff-Schwartz-Orcutt (protein)
  LG: Le-Gasquel (protein)
  WAG: Whelan-Goldman (protein)
  JC: Jukes-Cantor (DNA)
  Yang: Yang&amp;#39;s general reversible process model (DNA)

Notes:
  Greater number of threads may improve processing time, but implies greater memory requirement (default is 1).
  Running GRASP requires large memory and in most cases Java needs to be run with the option -Xmx20g,
  where 20g specifies that 20GB of RAM should be available.
  ~ This is version 4-July-2022 ~
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-else&#34;&gt;What else?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running the command-line version is typically a quicker affair, at least for smaller reconstructions, but it requires decent hardware. A reconstruction of less than 1,000 sequences should take less than 10 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can probably run a reconstruction with 10,000 sequences on a server, but how &amp;ldquo;gappy&amp;rdquo; the alignment is will also play a part in deciding this. If the alignment is reasonably clean, a powerful, modern laptop with at least 16GB of memory, can do this in under a day. If the alignment covers a diverse family, you will probably need a lot more memory. We recommend you set the Java heap size to 60GB RAM, which you can using the option -Xmx60000m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rough estimates above assume you use multiple threads; we recommend 5 or so on decent hardware (&amp;ndash;threads 5).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GRASP</title>
      <link>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/grasp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/grasp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;grasp-web-service&#34;&gt;GRASP web service&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GRASP web service was developed to facilitate the steps of performing a reconstruction of ancestor sequences (represented by partial-order graphs) and the exploration, archival and sharing of the output. The service consists of three major parts: an inference engine &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bodenlab/bnkit&#34;&gt;bnkit&lt;/a&gt; written in Java, a web service backend written in Java using the Spring framework and Postgres, and web client functionality written in Javascript. The latter two are contained in the open source project &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bodenlab/GRASP&#34;&gt;GRASP&lt;/a&gt;. GRASP depends on the open source project &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bodenlab/bnkit&#34;&gt;bnkit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grasp-what-can-it-do&#34;&gt;GRASP: What can it do?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://grasp.scmb.uq.edu.au&#34;&gt;GRASP web service&lt;/a&gt; has a User&amp;rsquo;s Guide that we recommend. You will find it in the menu at the top of the GRASP screen at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grasp-how-do-i-make-it-work-on-my-computer&#34;&gt;GRASP: How do I make it work on my computer?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use any standard web browser and enter the URL &lt;a href=&#34;http://grasp.scmb.uq.edu.au&#34;&gt;http://grasp.scmb.uq.edu.au&lt;/a&gt;. We recommend that you sign up for an account; with an account you will be able to use a lot of features that otherwise are unavailable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;graspcmd-how-do-i-run-it&#34;&gt;GraspCmd: How do I run it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the User&amp;rsquo;s Guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-else&#34;&gt;What else?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;command-line version&lt;/a&gt; to run reconstructions on your local hardware. This version does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have all the features; for instance there is no interactive mode and currently no way of transferring your reconstruction to the web service.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SeqScrub</title>
      <link>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/seqscrub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://bodenlab.github.io/GRASP-suite/project/seqscrub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
